welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
i'm maybe gray welcome to the stoa
this stoa is a digital campfire where we
can
cohere and discuss what's on the knife's
edge of what's happening now
i've been hosting a series of q as
called
raw sexuality on topics that are
sensitive and taboo in our culture
hoping
to start some radically honest
conversations
that we might not otherwise have and
today
i'm here with chester brown who is
the writer and illustrator of mary wept
over the feet of jesus
which i think has a radically honest
reinterpretation
of some of the norms around sexuality in
our culture um specifically from the
bible
um i
i'm sorry i i can hear my boyfriend
laughing at me again through the wall
and
it always makes me chuckle chester um
i was wondering if you could start us
off by telling us a little bit about
what inspired you to write
mary wept over the feet of jesus
um
okay many years ago but i mean i've i've
had an interest
in christianity for a long time i was
raised
religious i was raised in a in a in a
home
where you know we went to church every
sunday and um
and then and you know i i
i was a believer uh although
you know in my teenage years i went
through a questioning phase
um but then in my early 20s i started
reading
um books uh of
biblical scholarship uh and
got really fascinated with that and
began reading the bible
really seriously and um
then i did i decided uh
you know i got a comic book a publisher
hired me to do a comic book series and i
could basically do whatever i wanted
in it and so for part of it i decided
i'm super interested
in the subject of the you know religion
christianity the gospels why don't i do
um an adaptation of the of the gospels
and so i started with the gospel of mark
which was the earliest of the gospels
and um
so i was and that
made me focus even more on reading uh
works of biblical scholarship
and so i this would have been the 1980s
when i was
doing this and uh sometime in the 80s i
think around
87 or 1988 a book was published
um by this biblical scholar named jane
schaberg
the book was titled the illegitimacy of
jesus
and jane schaberg's uh contention
was that uh the virgin mary
uh uh had not been
versioned that that she had been
raped and that jesus was the result of
that that rape and
i read that and i was like yeah that
makes more sense than
the story that she was a virgin so i
pretty much just accepted
uh jane's uh proposal
and um um
and then and uh just
uh and and by the way the illegitimate
the illegitimacy of jesus is a great
book
uh even though i now disagree with some
of the conclusions in it
uh i i mean if you're into biblical
scholarship
like everyone should be reading that
book um but
so um so like i said i accepted her
conclusions
and um and
went on with things and then um
years later uh uh
totally unrelated i started uh visiting
prostitutes
started started paying for sex and um
that got me interested in you know
stories about prostitutes and
i was already into the bible so biblical
stories about prostitutes
and now going back to jane schaberg
part of her reason for believing
that um
that jesus had been illegitimate that
mary had been raped
was this genealogy in the gospel of
matthew
in that genealogy um
now biblical genealogies
usually just focus on men like uh
uh adam gave birth to seth who gave
birth to
uh micah who gave birth to whatever i'm
making up names but uh you know it's
it's a sequence of
men so such and such male begat such and
such male but
such and such male and the women are
totally ignored like the mothers are not
mentioned usually
in genealogies and matthew's genealogy
is different
it mostly focuses on men but
five women are mentioned in this
genealogy
the five women are uh let's see if i can
remember them off the top of my head
uh tamar rahab ruth
bathsheba and mary the
mary the mother of jesus um
and so jane schaberg
was like why did matthew
do this why did he mention five women
and not
other women in in that genealogy
and this is really strange because women
are not usually mentioned in genealogies
and she said um she pointed out
that the the first four women
are women who are somehow associated
with
um doing something
sexually unconventional um
outside of marriage um
uh tamar had been uh had had sex for
money
with with a man uh rahab had
been a prostitute uh had had sex with
multiple
men um ruth
had uh seduced a man in order to
get him to marry her and bathsheba
now bathsheba is the questionable one
but the
the the way that matthew probably would
have seen it
uh is that bathsheba uh
tempted king david into getting sexually
involved with her
and so that would have been you know
pre-marital sex
uh some people make the argument that
bathsheba
would have been uh could have been
she definitely could have been a rape
victim so that's the closest to
jane schaberg's theory that but anyways
jane schaberg was arguing
that the inclusion of these four women
in the genealogy
meant that um
that uh the virgin that mary had been
was a rape victim and i had accepted
that initially and
at a certain point i was like no only
only one of those women was a potential
rape victim
uh the first three were not two of them
were
having sex for money one of them uh
you know was deliberately
seduced a man and the fourth one
uh bathsheba she might have been a rape
victim
but it's more likely that matthew
actually the author of the gospel of
matthew wouldn't have been named matthew
but
i'm going to call him matthew just for
convenience sake uh matthew
probably did not see her as a rape
victim he probably saw her as a
temptress
so and that's probably he was probably
saying
the these four women um
they're connected to mary like
uh mary got pregnant in a way that was
similar to
these four women um so to me
it looked likely that mary uh
had um
had probably been a prostitute uh what
uh
if if we're supposed to connect those
four women to mary
uh why would two women who uh charge
money for sex
be in that list if prostitution wasn't
the anyway so uh i concluded that
that that's what matthew intended us
uh to see that that mary was
he was matthew was intending to hint
that mary was
a prostitute um
that's what it looked like to me so um
i'm trying to think where when would i
have come to that conclusion
probably the early 2000s or something
and so i was thinking oh i should do a
book about this
um but i couldn't think how to do it
so this idea was in my mind for many
years that
mary was probably a prostitute and how
do i turn that
into a book and you know i had other
books to work on so
uh so that's how it started that that
was the
initial germ of the idea for the book
so i don't know i when i went on a long
time there i
i don't know if you want to ask yeah
i i do have a follow-up question for
that i uh i'll point out here that we'll
probably take a couple questions maybe
back and forth between the two of us but
uh within the next like 15 minutes here
open it up two questions from the chat
so i encourage anybody as questions come
up to
type them in the chat this is being
recorded so if you would prefer not to
appear in the youtube video you can just
indicate that you would prefer for me to
read your question for you
but that being said i'm curious chester
one of the things that you mentioned
in uh mary wept over the feet of jesus
is that
matthew let's call him uh wouldn't have
been able to just come right out
and say that that mary wasn't a virgin
and i wonder uh what you see as the
reasons
in the past and in the present why
people would
want to present mary as either
immaculate and
pure or as wronged rather than having
made it
like some sort of choice with her
sexuality
um yeah i i
uh i mean the the the very idea that
mary was a virgin um
i don't think and and this was also
another uh
one of the things that um jane schaberg
contended was that the idea that mary
was a virgin
is not a biblical idea she argued that
it's nowhere in the bible it's not in
matthew and it's not in luke um
that it wasn't matthew or luke or
or any of the biblical writers who
contended that she was a virgin
it was the readers of
matthew and luke early on who didn't
want to accept
the obvious implication of the story
that matthew
and luke incidentally luke is
is another of the of the gospel uh
i mean there are four gospels four four
books in the bible
that basically tell the story about
jesus matthew mark
luke and john and so the the two stories
that
tell the story that tell about um
uh the birth of jesus uh that tell the
story about
mary and uh joseph the
the you know the the two people who
raised jesus
um those come from matthew and luke
and yeah if you really examine them
neither of them says that mary was a
virgin it's
it's people early christians
didn't want to accept the implication
that mary got
pregnant uh by having sex with a man
other than joseph the man she eventually
married
and that she was having that she had at
least
had to have had sex with at least one
man outside of wedlock
you know prior to marrying joseph uh
the the early christians didn't want to
accept that so they invented this story
about the virginity of of mary
and it's difficult now for people
reading those stories
to see that they um
read matthew and luke and kind of
project um
that idea onto them project the idea
that
and i mean there are reasons for that uh
say in luke um
the first time i think mary is referred
to in the story she is referred to
as a virgin um but
just saying that she's a virgin when
she's introduced into the story doesn't
mean she stays a virgin
and that she is still a virgin after she
becomes pregnant with jesus and actually
if you read luke after she gets pregnant
she is never
again referred to as a virgin so
and you know it's it's similar in
matthew
um so um
both matthew and luke were trying were
being
coy like they didn't want to
they didn't want to emphasize what was
going on
uh you know that mary had sex with some
other guy other than joseph
but they made it pretty clear that she
didn't
and um so they're kind of
because they were coy about it because
they didn't want to be too
they they were trying to uh indicate
that mary
had gods that god approved of
the birth of jesus um without
emphasizing too strongly
what how mary actually got
pregnant like um they wanted to take the
emphasis off that
but they didn't want to it's now what i
think i didn't actually put this in the
book
but now what i think is going because i
was wondering
why um
why would they admit okay in the case of
matthew
why would he even want to hint that mary
had been a
a a a prostitute if he was embarrassed
about it
why just why include that information in
the genealogy why not
um um
not deal with it at all maybe even skip
the birth of jesus
or or or whatever
and so uh if i was writing
the the matthew chapter now that i in
in mary wept over the feet of jesus um
i would i would change it
um the reason why i think they
hinted at it was because too many people
knew i suspect that what was going on
okay matthew and luke they weren't the
first gospels the very first gospel
is the gospel of mark and mark
there's no birth of jesus story in there
and barely he barely discusses the
mother of jesus
and i think now
what what happened is that people were
making fun of the early christians they
were saying
yeah you can't even admit like you wrote
this
you had you wrote this book the gospel
of mark and you had to ignore
the the birth of jesus because you were
embarrassed about
his mother and i think that
forced matthew and luke
to at least deal with the the birth just
to some degree
to um to
admit that there was that that uh
mary had not gotten pregnant uh by
having sex with joseph
that she got pregnant out of wedlock
prior to being with joseph
and i think they were kind of forced to
admit it
and but they kind of
skipped over that information
they included the information but but
dealt with it in such a way that they
didn't have to
yeah they as i said they were being
quiet about it
and uh so now that's what i think
uh was going on that that they were
forced to it by by the critics of
christianity um and then because
they weren't explicit because they
didn't say exactly
who got married pregnant when and how
and where
um uh
then then subsequent christians were
able to
read that story as being the story about
uh
a miraculous virgin birth
um i i think it's really fascinating how
you understand jesus and
his life in light of knowing
about his own birth and that it was
like socially frowned upon in some way
could you speak a little bit about that
um yeah there's
uh um i i think
jesus did uh
i mean there are several hints about
this elsewhere in
early christian writings um in the
gospel of john for instance
jesus gets involved in a debate
with um some some people who
apparently disagree with him and
um they're kind of trading insults back
and forth
and at one point um
these these i think they're pharisees or
jewish scribes or something
they they they say something like
uh our mothers were
weren't prostitutes and
prior to this there'd been no discussion
about anyone's mothers or anyone being a
prostitute
so why did they bring it up it seemed to
be uh
a hint that uh that that jesus
had been uh his mother had been a
prostitute
so i i uh obviously and then there's a
similar thing in the gospel of uh
there's a similar reference to the
gospel
of uh thomas um where
uh uh
it says something about um
i'm trying to think uh i can't remember
the exact wording but it refers to
uh it that jesus was the son of a whore
or something like that
um so um
uh so i think jesus drew up
uh knowing about his mother's
uh background and and knowing that she
had been a prostitute
and i think this resulted in him
uh you know there are there's already a
belief
um and there are certain indications in
like
there's uh a
saying in the gospel of matthew where uh
jesus says you know prostitutes are
getting into heaven ahead of you and
he's talking to but again i think
pharisees there
um or jewish elders um
which seems to anyways um
so so there's already this idea
that people have that jesus uh
was tolerant of prostitution and that he
was forgiving of them and i don't i
think it goes beyond that i don't think
he
just had i don't think he just tolerated
them i think there was something
else going on and that's that leads to
uh another chapter in um
mary wept over the feet of jesus um
i came across an alternate version
of one of the
parables of jesus the parable of the
talents
um and now
in this parable in the biblical version
of of the parable it's a story about a
rich man who's going away
on a trip and he
um he calls
his three most trusted slaves to him
and he says i'm going away on this trip
but i want you to take care of my
money while i'm gone so um
and uh i'm gonna give
um i'm trying to remember the
the the amounts i think it was five
talents
to my most trusted slave uh
three talents to my second most trusted
slave
and one talent to uh my third most
trusted slave
and i want you to take care of the money
for me while i'm away
and when i come back
and i'll i'm going to come back sometime
a year or two from now and so
uh while he's away the two most trusted
slaves they both invest the money and
they double the money and the the one
who's
less trusted the one who only got one
talent he
takes that one talent and buries it in
the ground and
thereby uh keeps it safe and
so when the master comes back uh the
the two most trusted slaves are able to
say to the master
we doubled your money and uh so the
master's happy with them
and the slave who buried the money
he um the master is
very unhappy with him and he's he um
says you know get out of my sight and
this has always
puzzled christians because it makes it
look like jesus
is super concerned about money and
investing money and doubling your money
which totally contradicts everything
that jesus says
you know elsewhere in the gospels where
he's
like don't be concerned about money like
don't uh
you shouldn't worry about these sorts of
things um
so um
i was i was reading a book uh
i think in 2014 i was reading a book
about um the parables of jesus
and so it was by the
book was by this biblical or i don't
think he's
officially a biblical scholar well he's
he's a historian
and he's super interested in the bible
uh this guy
john dominic crossin um
and so uh i believe the book's title is
the power of parable uh
or the power of parables something like
that
so in the section of the book where he's
dealing with the
parable of the talent of the talents
he mentions and i had never heard this
before
that there's an alternate version of
this story which was given by the early
church um father historian
um eusebius who if i'm remembering
correctly i think he lived around
8300 um
i hope i don't have that too wrong or
too off but anyway
um uh so eusebius said
that uh
the earliest ver in the earliest version
of the gospel of matthew
there's an alternate version of the uh
parable of the talents and so
um in that version
uh the the rich
master is going away and again he
in this version he also calls his three
most trusted slaves to him
and says to you know uh to the most
trusted one yeah
i'm giving you five talents to the
second most trusted one i'm giving you
three and to the least trusted one
and then he goes away but in this
version of the story
um the
uh the most trusted one well um
eusebius's telling of the story is a bit
unclear
so who he gives the money to and
who spends the money in which way is
it's a bit muddled uh but one of
the one of the slaves spends all the
money on prostitutes
and one of them uh invests the money and
doubles it
and again one of them buries it and
uh you know just ends up uh with
just the the the one talent he was given
or that
what the amount that he was given uh and
then
when uh the master comes back
he's very pleased with one of these
slaves
he's not so pleased with a another one
and he's uh
he apparently again the uh he's unhappy
with the
the slave who buried the talent um
and it's unclear was he happy with the
with the with the slave who spent all
the money
on prostitutes that's how i think this
story
there i get into a large
uh into a lengthy uh discussion of why i
think
that this is the way that the ma that
jesus
originally told the story that the
master when he comes back
he embraces the slave who
spent all the money on prostitutes and
he
um
is less happy with the slave who doubled
the money and he's least happy with the
with the slave who buried the the talent
um and if i'm right
then it indicates that g that jesus
um didn't just
tolerate prostitution that he
actually saw it as socially beneficial
i think that's what the parable is is
telling us
um and yeah i give
uh i'm not sure that it's that
convincing when i'm telling it right now
uh i hope it's convincing in all my in
my lengthy endnotes why i explain why
i think the master in the story embraces
the the the one who spent the money on
prostitutes
uh but yeah that's my main reason for
thinking that jesus
saw prostitution is socially beneficial
i so enjoy your adaptation of the
parable of the talents because i think
it really
um gets at the exact intersection
between
um prostitution and this sort of broader
um
like reward for some sorts of religious
disobedience
like the idea that god or jesus aren't
actually looking for us to like follow
the letter of the law
compared to the way that they're looking
for us to like have faith and
and try to have a good life for
ourselves
um i i think that um tyler's question
um would be really interesting to move
into from here
tyler could you unmute yourself
yeah sorry i was washing the dishes
i was i was curious chester how your
relationship to christianity
has changed over time whether you still
consider yourself a christian
maybe you consider yourself like a sort
of almost alternate christian
who has a christian adjacent belief
system but that includes things like
sacred prostitution uh that set of
questions
yeah i i i i i
when i when i first became obsessed with
reading about all this sort of stuff
back in the 80s um
i was reading all this biblical
scholarship that
kind of it's it initially seemed to tear
apart the gospels
and um it made it
difficult to continue to believe
that you know the the gospels or the by
the material in the bible is the word of
god
when you can when you understand how it
was all put together and everything
um so that kind of shook my faith uh
for a while and i was um
for a while for a year or two
maybe longer than that i was defining
myself as an agnostic
um but
then i started getting more into
what is called uh the gnostic material
um that made more
sense to me that the idea that
um a sense the divine was more
uh that you got it more from in
inside yourself than from relying on
outwardly
on sets of writings by other people
now since then i've i've
um a biblical scholar named
karen king has sort of deconstructed the
idea that there
actually was an ancient group called
gnostics
uh but of course there were
writings that that uh that
that did later get defined or uh as
as as gnosticism so i guess it's
well it's it's a contentious term but
anyways uh basically i'm saying i found
a way back
into um the
the religion and um
so for a while i i was
i was back to considering myself
religious and believing in god but
it's like i don't have to define myself
as a christian anymore
um eventually i decided
why like i'm obviously obsessed with
this stuff like i'm
reading about jesus all the time
and i believe there's a god and
this is my
understanding of
my like my understanding
of god comes through
the christian stories the parables
the um the story about jesus
um the uh
the the the metaphors that are used in
christianity the
the the the rituals it's uh like
this this if i'm so obsessed with it and
i'm religious
why not call myself christian one of the
reasons
why i shouldn't is because
i don't look like a christian to so many
christians my beliefs are so unorthodox
but like why worry about that um so
these days yes
i define myself as a christian and i
don't worry about
uh what other what other christians say
if other christians don't want to
consider me a christian that's fine
uh it's not a big deal um
yeah tyler i see you have a follow-up
question in the chat i would love if you
unmuted yourself again and asked that
too
yeah um just i was i was curious
you know one place i thought um this
talk might be leading is that you might
have thoughts on how
prostitution itself can be a spiritual
practice
not not just the idea that in the bible
you know people like mary might have
actually been prostitutes but that
um prostitution has a place sort of in
in religion so i'd be curious to get
your thoughts on that
in religion or or sacred practice yeah
um the the
well prostitution
was certainly honored in lots of ancient
um religion religions particularly
several of the the goddess religions
um after i
wrote mary wept over the feet of jesus
a translation of the the texts
devoted to the ancient goddess inanna
came out um i'm trying to think
they were translated by a toronto
writer um i can't remember her name off
the top of my head a
kim something i think i'm i i apologize
to her if
she's probably not hearing this but but
um
but in in that in though that
translation of these
you know ancient texts devoted to this
goddess there are plenty devoted to
to prostitutes and you know extolling
prostitutes and their their role in
society and how they benefit
society and you know it wouldn't have
just been
that religion there were plenty of
ancient goddess religions
that that that honored prostitution
and i suspect
that that's what was going on
that jesus was somehow related to that
um
another part of mary wept over the feet
of jesus
is the sequence in the bible
where jesus is um
anointed by
a woman and
it's pretty clear this is in all for the
gospels matthew mark
and john all have this scene
where a woman anoints jesus and this
is important because that's what the
word
christ means it means anointed one
that's what a messiah was a messiah was
an anointed one
and this is
in the gospels this is the only time
that jesus
is anointed he's and
um the
it's pretty clear certainly in
the gospel of luke the the woman is
referred to as a sinner and
um it
everyone interprets that as the you know
luke meaning that the woman was a
prostitute
um and
i'm trying to think i think in
uh mark
mark and matthew they're not as clear
but it's it's this woman who who comes
and anoints jesus
but then the significant uh gospel in
this regards in
in regards to this story is the gospel
of john
um because in in
john's recounting of the story and again
john
the gospel john was not written by a guy
named john i'm going to call him john
uh in john's version of the story
um the the woman who annoys jesus
is named and her her name is mary of
bethany
and um mary
of in in this version of this story
um mary of
mary um has her hair uncovered
she's not referred to as a prostitute
but she has her hair uncovered
and this is not something women
conventionally did
at that time in in jewish society at
that time women kept their head
their hair covered because hair was seen
as being
erotically alluring like a woman who
exposed her hair it would have been the
equivalent today of a woman
of a woman bearing her breasts and a
woman
would not have done that in a ceremony
like this and it's it's clear that her
hair is exposed
as she's anointing jesus um
so it's it
seems pretty clear she's a prostitute
the prostitutes were the women at that
time
who exposed their hair um
and uh so so
this dovetails with luke calling her a
sinner
um so uh
yeah it seems pretty clear and so why is
jesus being
anointed by a prostitute
um unless this
this is um
this relates to it
i it's my impression that
jesus was involved in a form of judaism
that honored not just the male god
yahweh but also the female goddess
asherah and there are references in
ancient texts to
yahweh the jewish god having a female
consort
named asherah actually there's some
debate about
whether ashrae is actually a name
there's also a debate about whether
yahweh is actually a name but let's
avoid all that let's we're going to call
them we're going to say that their names
were yahweh and ashrae
so i think jesus was involved
in some sort of
organization that had been
it had been a part of judaism although
not formally acknowledged in the
jewish texts but it had been
uh part of judaism for centuries i think
and and i mean it is acknowledged in the
jewish text to the degree that you can
see
that um uh
a certain that the jewish
priests were constantly trying to purge
uh goddess worship from judaism
and there's there are lots of references
to
um to worshipers of baal
being executed and it seems obvious to
me that
these this was a part of judaism
that this was an internal war of sorts
within judaism
and the the faction
that wanted to say that that wanted to
define
uh judaism as a monotheistic
uh a religion ruled over by one male god
that's the faction that went out but it
wasn't the only
part it wasn't the only uh faction
within judaism
that there had been a faction that
was into goddess worship that honored
uh god as having both a male and female
aspect is perhaps a better way to say it
does that answer your question tyler
maybe i got off
it topic very interesting but not
exactly uh i was sort of
more interested in um chester's own
personal views
on how uh prostitution might be seen as
a spiritual practice
like today in the world uh
well i think every aspect of life
can be seen as holy or religious
um like i do uh
i pay for sex um i've i've
had a relationship with one particular
sex worker for
17 years now and uh
when i'm with her yeah it's
i mean it's it's a it's a sexual
experience but it also
is holy it's it's uh
um i try to honor it as
the the sex we have as being special
i mean it definitely is special to me
and and
i see it as something that is uh
uh god given uh just like i
try and see i mean i've approached life
from a religious perspective i
i'm always trying to see to experience
walking through life as if i'm walking
through
heaven i see this realm as being very
heaven-like while admitting that you
know
uh there are aspects that uh might not
seem
as heavenly so heavenly to a lot of
people
um i i think it would be interesting to
go to jeff's question
it was earlier in the chat so jeff let
me know if you need me to like copy it
for you to find it again but if you
remember it you can unmute yourself and
ask
hey yeah i remember it um
i've been thinking before i read your
book a lot about jesus
and like how his parents must have been
badass so on some level
um and so when i got to that part of
matthew in your book i
had a very strong emotional reaction to
it and i liked it a lot
um uh i'm sure you've gotten like lots
of bad criticism since the book was
written like my own mother was like this
guy's out to lunch
but uh have you had any like you've
already talked about a few but i'm like
really interested if like any good
critical engagement
since then that maybe or uh
more things that have come up um since
writing the book like
uh uh ideas that maybe people agree with
you and
and uh or disagree with you that maybe
pushed the
idea forward a bit more yeah i guess uh
i mean you refer to to um
me talking about our earlier uh
experiences
probably the one that you're thinking of
is like i have a very close friend
who is a christian
and she was um
actually when when the book came out i
said
you know maybe you don't want to read
this book like
this book isn't for everyone like we're
good friends like
i i don't want to jeopardize a
friendship and
she was like no no no i really want to
read it and of course then she read it
and she was totally offended and
upset with me and and um
but but then she she came around
and and um
particularly in the years since then
she has gotten involved
in really um studying biblical
scholarship and
now she understands more uh where where
i'm where i was coming from
and uh now we're back to being very good
friends uh i saw her just yesterday
um and um
but uh you're probably thinking of or
asking about
if there's been stuff since then
um i don't know i mean
this is relatively an old book by now
it came out in 2016 and so in the last
few years
um
like i still i still
go go on um which i'll call it goodreads
and keep up with the reviews that one
sees there
and when the book first came out there
were all sorts of people who hated the
book
as well as people who really loved the
book um
and uh but
that was in the maybe
the first six months or the first year
of when the book was
released and since then there continued
to be people posting reviews
and for whatever reason um
now it's getting almost exclusively
positive reviews from people on a source
like that
and i'm not sure why
initially it was divided between
negative reactions and positive
reactions
um maybe that's because of the initial
uh publicity around the book and so more
people who
uh maybe have a religious nature
uh were encountering
hearing the about the book and now it's
more
word of mouth readers and so
that that's maybe kind of a
self-selection process that results in
uh just uh people
positively encountering the book but um
but yeah i haven't had a lot of uh
negative reaction
in the last few years to the book
um jacob would you like to unmute
yourself and ask your question
sort of um
so chester uh regarding
christ's view of prostitution
uh we not say that
we can discern his view of it
based on his obvious reference for the
mosaic law so for example
he constantly was upholding the law and
referencing it right he would say
it is written it is written as written
have you not read have you not read how
does the law read
who's constantly referring to it
referring to it as his
touchstone right source of truth in fact
even when he committed
when he performed healings he would say
now go show yourself to the priest
so he was still encouraging
adherence to the law even right before
he was about to abolish it
so it's impossible to read the
scriptures from the hebrew to the greek
without being very clear how christ
feels about the mosaic law the mosaic
law says in leviticus
uh do not profane your daughter by
making her a prostitute
and then there's another instance in
leviticus where it says something like
if the daughter of a priest profanes
herself by prostitution
and then some sort of consequence is
listed so
to me it's like how could christ
uphold prostitution uh at the expense of
the clarity
where the law stands clearly on on
prostitution
um well the
the problem with that is
did jesus have reverence for the mosaic
law now
if if one um
it's it that seems to be the case if one
reads the gospel of matthew
matthew is totally f he's obsessed with
the mosaic law
and um it's a big deal for matthew to
establish jesus within
jewish history and i mean that's partly
why there's that genealogy
um in matthew um
and and yeah but but
did matthew get jesus
right um i mean this is a question
right from the beginning of the the
gospels
the first gospel was the gospel as i've
said the gospel of mark
did mark understand
jesus um
mark um
there's an odd thing about mark which is
um
mark uh presents
the story of jesus from the beginning of
jesus's ministry
up until uh jesus's crucifixion and if
you know a few days after that um
uh but mark has this
uh odd take uh
not just on jesus but on the disciples
of jesus
mark is continually presenting the
disciples
of jesus as being stupid is not
understanding
jesus's message um this
is this is one of the big
messages of mark which is the the
the apostles of of jesus didn't
understand him
um who understands jesus
mark understands jesus now mark
never never met jesus how likely is it
that mark understood jesus better than
the disciples of jesus
i think jesus i think mark
had his particular understanding of who
jesus was
but his understanding was in conflict
with the message that the disciples had
the the disciples of jesus were probably
still
alive uh when jesus oh sorry
when mark was writing his gospel
and um so
mark if he wanted his version of jesus
to be under uh to be accepted
had to downplay the the disciples of
jesus
had to say these guys did not understand
jesus they were stupid they were idiots
um and so uh
that so that's uh so i'm i i really
don't think
mark is conveying the the
genuine teachings of jesus uh i i think
there's probably some genuine teachings
of jesus mixed in there
but uh i think he's um
uh you know presenting some
probably some stuff he's getting from
paul
who also never met jesus and uh
some stuff maybe he get he got from
other sources
but um he's definitely
saying stuff that the disciples of jesus
weren't saying
like he's contradicting the the
disciples of jesus now
matthew who is the the
gospel writer who really stresses
jesus's reverence
for the mosaic law matthew's
gospel is a rewritten version of mark's
gospel
so
matthew's gospel is um
it's it's a step removed it's it's
even one more step removed from jesus
and it's based on a source that is
unlikely to be faithful to the teachings
of jesus
basically that's what i'm saying so how
how much reverence did jesus really have
for the mosaic law
i don't i suspect he he did respect it
to some degree
and and did see the mosaic law as as uh
doing as as being uh an important part
of
of jewish tradition um there is
what was it he he's talking about uh
divorce law
and he said he he talks about um
how uh moses uh
gave in to your desire for uh
for the divorce which is an indication
that he thinks
that um the mosaic law
was was not necessarily divinely
inspired that
moses was inventing at least aspects of
the mosaic law
but anyways that that's like you
probably disagree which is fine we don't
have to agree on everything well
it just seems like your answer is just
simply well the record's wrong
and i think that's way too easy way too
thank you thanks for your answer you're
welcome
um chester are there any uh final
thoughts that you'd like to leave us
with as we're just coming up on the end
of the hour
um
no i'm i nothing's coming to mind really
um yeah every everything it's it's been
a
it's been a wow that hour went fast it's
been a
very nice experience uh doing this
thank you so much for being here yeah
it's been a great experience i
am so excited to uh get a little bit
more
uh background on on a graphic novel that
i just
enjoyed start to finish especially the
religious scholarship in the back maybe
if if jacob were to read your full notes
on uh why you believe what you believe
he might feel
slightly more persuaded um i
i think if you guys like this q a uh you
would
have a lot of fun at a new wisdom gym
event
that we have coming up tomorrow with uh
doug tatteren
uh from his bio motive process he's
gonna be doing a live demo
um of some emotional process thing uh
which i
i always find uh working with doug and
watching
doug work with others to be very like
sacred and spiritual and lovely
um i'm just double checking sorry for my
my uh unpreparedness uh what time that
is oh
uh it's tomorrow uh at 2 15 p.m eastern
so if you are free for this and your
schedule looks the same tomorrow you
should be free for that
um also tomorrow we have a session
with andrew taggart and daniel from
metagame mastermind
uh called the philosopher is present um
andrew is going to be sitting in and
asking
questions to people in the audience so
it's going to be a q a
except the queues are coming your way
this time i think that'll be really fun
i think it'll be a fun inverted format
so definitely
check that out as well that's tomorrow
at 6 pm eastern
and again thank you so much chester for
being here
um the stoa is a gift so if you are
inspired to give a gift in return you
can always vote visit the stoa
dot ca gift um and make sure you check
out uh
mary wept over the feet of jesus and
also paying for it which are uh
chester's most recent graphic novels oh
yeah i have mine too
and then also paying for it both like
tremendously funny
made me laugh made me cry and had
actually very important
insights in his notes in the back and i
really enjoyed them all
thanks everybody thank you maybe
oh we're going to be recording until
peter rescues you
then thank you peter and camille oh yes
thank you
yeah i don't know how this thing
operates
yeah this is chester's first time on
zoom
yes it's like his zoom birthday
i